[{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"1. Speakers of this city’s Cheli dialect participated in a 1970s counterculture movement known as this city’s “Movida.” This city’s Carabanchel Prison was used to house political prisoners during the rule of a dictator who erected the Valley of the Fallen in one of this city’s suburbs. A set of Accords signed in this European capital city handed over control of Western Sahara to Morocco and Mauritania. The 1975 coronation of Juan Carlos I in this city marked the end of a dictatorship ruled by the Falange Party. For 10 points, name this capital city that served as the base of Francisco Franco’s regime. ","answer":"ANSWER: Madrid "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"2. Description acceptable. In a play set during this historical event, Ned Weeks pressures Felix Turner to write an article about this event for the New York Times. The nurse Belize treats people impacted by this historical event in a play that ends with the characters gathering around the Bethesda Fountain. Randy Shilts’ And The Band Played On is about this event, which, in another play, leads to the death of a man who is visited by Ethel Rosenberg’s ghost in his hospital room. In that play, Roy Cohn fears that his death during this disease outbreak will reveal his homosexuality. For 10 points, name this epidemic central to Tony Kushner’s Angels in America. ","answer":"ANSWER: the AIDS epidemic [or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome; accept the AIDS crisis; accept HIV in the place of AIDS; accept any answer that mentions AIDS or HIV] (the play described in the first line is Larry Kramer’s The Normal Heart) "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"3. Sir James Edward Smith founded a society named for this man, where papers by Alfred Wallace were read at the first public exposition on the theory of evolution. The 17 “apostles” of this man travelled with explorers like James Cook to help him gather plant specimens from around the world to study at Uppsala. Cladistics is an extension of a system developed by this man, which splits the biological world into plants, animals and minerals. This man’s book Systema Naturae helped found the modern field of taxonomy. For 10 points, name this Swedish naturalist who popularized binomial nomenclature. ","answer":"ANSWER: Carolus Linnaeus [or Carl Linnaeus] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"4. In 2017, Ai Weiwei protested U.S border control by placing a giant Gilded Cage in this place. A memorial in this location was designed by Bruce Kelly, who fought to preserve this place. A controversial photo taken here depicts an exasperated child holding a toy hand grenade, and was shot by Diane Arbus. Bright orange structures were installed throughout this location for Jean-Claude and Christo’s 2005 installation The Gates. This place, home to one of three of Cleopatra’s Needles, was designed by landscape architects Calvert Vaux and Frederick Law Olmsted. For 10 points, name this public space bordering the Met and Guggenheim, a large park in New York City. ","answer":"ANSWER: Central Park [prompt on New York City; prompt on NYC; prompt on Manhattan] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"5. A text by this philosopher distinguishes between two forms of self-love by tracing one back to village music contests. That text by this philosopher defines the distinction between man and animal as “perfectibility,” or the ability of man to learn by observing others. This philosopher argued that private property was created when the first man fenced in a piece of land to declare it his. This author of Discourse on Inequality distinguished between the government and the “sovereign of the general will” in a book that declares that “man is born free, and everywhere he is in chains.” For 10 points, name this philosopher of The Social Contract. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jean-Jacques Rousseau "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"6. The narrator of this short story observes “the Rubicon passed, one lends himself to the occasion” after a man requests a glass of wine for his passed-out wife. This story, which is the second entry in Evenings at Medan, begins with a stagecoach journey to Tôtes, during which the protagonist surprises her fellow passengers by sharing a picnic basket. Cornudet [“cor-noo-DAY”] whistles “La Marseillaise” [“mar-say-AZE”] at the end of this story, whose title character weeps after a group of nobles shame her into sleeping with a Prussian officer. For 10 points, name this story about the prostitute Elisabeth Rousset [“roo-SAY”], written by Guy de Maupassant. ","answer":"ANSWER: “Ball of Fat” [or “Boule de Suif”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"7. In one religious tradition, this ceremony is assisted by a ragyapa, who helps a priest burn juniper incense. Timothy Leary wrote a “manual” based on a Nyingma text usually read at these ceremonies, which describes six transitory states of consciousness called bardos. In one tradition, these ceremonies are performed on a raised structure divided into three concentric circles, known as Towers of Silence. The traditional “sky” form of this ceremony practiced in Tibet originated when priests could not find enough firewood to perform cremation. For 10 points, name this type of ceremony at which Buddhists might read The Tibetan Book of the Dead to console a deceased person’s family. ","answer":"ANSWER: funerals [or burials; accept sky burials; prompt on descriptive answers that mention death or the treatment of dead bodies] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"8. Jones and Mueller matrices can be used to calculate how this property changes as light propagates through a system. As light passes through a magnetic field, it undergoes a rotational change in this property in the Faraday effect. Birefringent materials are used to make half-wave plates, which can reverse the sign of this property. A light ray not having this property will gain this property when approaching a surface at Brewster’s angle. This property, whose varieties include linear and circular, is used by some sunglasses to reduce glare. For 10 points, name this property which can describes the orientation of a light wave’s oscillations. ","answer":"ANSWER: polarization [accept word forms, but do not accept “polarizability”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"9. One person with this title names an “Assurance” given to Patriarch Sophronius of Jerusalem. Another person of this title rejected a woman’s claim to inheriting Fadak. The first holder of this title launched the Ridda Wars to unify his domain. A holder of this title defeated a Byzantine army commanded by Vahan the Armenian in a battle fought near the Yarmouk River. While praying, one holder of this title was killed with a poison-tipped sword wielded by a Kharijite. The First Fitna began after the assassination of one holder of this title, Uthman, who was succeeded by Ali. For 10 points, give this title of four “Rightly-Guided” leaders of Islam. ","answer":"ANSWER: Rashidun Caliph [or Rightly-Guided Caliph] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"0. This material is traditionally used by the artisan sculptors of Dongyang, China. In Greek acrolithic sculptures, body parts were sculpted from marble, while the torso and drapery were made from this material. Mary holds a particularly emaciated Christ in a Pieta sculpted from this material found in Röttgen, Germany. A technique utilizing this material was used to print the ukiyo-e of Hiroshige and Hokusai. Thunderbird is often depicted in tall sculptures of this material created by the Haida and Tlingit tribes of the Pacific Northwest. For 10 points, name this material used for the majority of African sculpture, as well as totem poles. ","answer":"ANSWER: wood "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"1. Lapis lazuli owes its color to an anion made of three atoms of this element. This element can be extracted from salt domes through a process that uses superheated water and three concentric tubes. The most common allotrope of this element has eight atoms in a puckered ring. The Claus process recovers this element from natural gas production. This element, which is found with lead in galena, can be industrially extracted using the Frasch process. Mercaptans and thiols are so named because they contain atoms of this element, which lies under oxygen on the periodic table. For 10 points, name this nonmetal that often forms compounds that smell like rotten eggs. ","answer":"ANSWER: sulfur [or S before mentioned] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"2. A boy in this novel uses his grandmother’s cane to kill a rattlesnake, impressing Otto Fuchs. Though he lives with his conservative grandparents, the narrator of this novel parties at the Owl Club with Lena Lingard. The violin-playing father of this novel’s protagonist kills himself in a barn after a difficult winter; later in this novel, the protagonist is impregnated by Larry Donovan, who abandons her. Twenty years after the main events of the novel, its narrator visits Anton Cuzak’s family in Black Hawk, Nebraska. For 10 points, name this novel about Jim Burden’s experiences growing up with the title Czech immigrant, written by Willa Cather. ","answer":"ANSWER: My Ántonia "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"3. The term “American exceptionalism” was first used to attack a leader of this organization named Jay Lovestone. Harry Hay split off from this organization to found the pro-LGBT Mattachine Society. Members of this organization were denied passports under the McCarran Act and prosecuted for violating the Smith Act. At a speech in Wheeling, West Virginia, a politician claimed to possess a list of 205 State Department employees associated with this political party. Alleged members of this organization were forced to testify before the House Un-American Activities Committee. For 10 points, name this American political party targeted by Joseph McCarthy during the Second Red Scare. ","answer":"ANSWER: Communist Party of the United States of America [or CPUSA] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"4. In the early 20th century, perennialists like Robert Maynard Hutchins advocated a normative approach to this field, in contrast to the “progressive” theories of this discipline favored by thinkers like Rudolf Steiner. The “banking model” was critiqued by a Brazilian theorist in this field named Paulo Freire. John Dewey emphasized the role of experience in a book whose title pairs this field with Democracy. Horace Mann’s reforms in Massachusetts were inspired by innovations made in this field by Maria Montessori. For 10 points, pedagogy is the study of what process by which students acquire knowledge? ","answer":"ANSWER: education [or learning; or teaching; or pedagogy until it is read] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"5. A June New Yorker article by Jelani Cobb uses this company’s buildings to illustrate Elijah Anderson’s concept of “white space.” In 2015, this company was widely mocked for its “#RaceTogether” [“hashtag race together”] campaign, which encouraged its employees to start conversations with customers about civil rights This company instituted mandatory racial bias training for all of its US employees after two black men were mistakenly arrested for trespassing at one of its stores in Philadelphia. This company pledged to hire 10,000 refugees under the leadership of its former CEO Howard Schultz. For 10 points, name Seattle-based coffee shop chain. ","answer":"ANSWER: Starbucks Coffee "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"6. One poem in this collection asks the reader to “choose” between “a shade, in which to sing” and “a grave, on which to rest from singing.” Another poem from this collection tells the reader to “gather the north flowers to complete the south.” A “mystic shape” holds the speaker of one poem in this collection before revealing itself to be “not Death, but Love;” the speaker of that poem from this collection reflects how “Theocritus had sung / of the sweet years.” The writer of this collection entreats the reader to “call me by my pet name” and pledges to “count the ways” she “loves thee.” For 10 points, name this poetry collection by Elizabeth Barrett Browning. ","answer":"ANSWER: Sonnets from the Portuguese "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"7. This city’s general Pagondus capitalized on the enemy army’s friendly fire to win the Battle of Delium. A statue of a lion commemorates this city’s defeat in a battle at which a general remarked that this city’s soldiers “never did or suffered anything unseemly.” As a youth, Philip II lived in this city as a hostage of its ruler Pelopidas. This capital of the Boeotian [“BEE-ocean”] League freed the Messenian helots from Sparta under its king Epaminondas. A battalion of gay lovers known as this city’s “Sacred Band” died at the Battle of Chaeronea [“kay-roh-NEE-uh”]. For 10 points, name this “seven-gated” city legendarily ruled by Cadmus and Oedipus. ","answer":"ANSWER: Thebes "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"8. This structure is the defining characteristic separating the fish in subclass Dipnoi [“dip-NOH-eye”] from all other extant species of Sarcopterygii [“sar-cop-TARE-uh-jee”]. Although it is evolutionarily unrelated to this structure, arachnids possess stacks of hemolymph-filled tissue known as the “book” form of this organ. This organ in terrestrial mammals is homologous to the swim bladders used by many species of fish to control buoyancy. In humans, its parenchymal [“pah-REN-kuh-mull”] tissue contains hollow cavities called alveoli, which are connected to bronchioles. For 10 points, name this vital organ that conducts the function of gas exchange within land-dwelling vertebrates. ","answer":"ANSWER: lungs [or book lungs; or lungfish] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"9. These people had a pantheon composed of the seventy sons of Bull El, known to them as King Father of Years. These people shared a group of stories named for the “Cycle” of one of their gods, which is written in the Ugaritic language. This group of people is said to be descended from a man who was cursed after seeing his father Noah naked. This group of people originated worship of Baal, Dagon, and Asherah and believed in an underworld known as Sheol. For 10 points, name this group of people, who are wiped out by the Israelites in the Book of Joshua. ","answer":"ANSWER: Canaanites [accept Phoenicians until stated] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"0. In an opera by this composer, a man sings “Come away, fellow sailors” to lead a short dance before a character plots to cause a sea storm in the aria “Our next motion.” A chorus sings “With drooping wings, ye cupids come” at the end of a scene in an opera by this composer set in a grove. A character in an opera by this composer tells her servant she is “prest with torment” in the aria “Ah, Belinda.” This composer worked with the librettist Nahum Tate on an opera that includes the aria “When I am laid in earth.” For 10 points, name this Baroque composer of the first major English-language opera, Dido and Aeneas. ","answer":"ANSWER: Henry Purcell Tiebreaker. On the advice of a monk, a holder of this office screamed “victory!” to overcome his cowardice while defending his country against an invasion. One holder of this office reconciled the rival claims of the Northern and Southern Courts. Holders of this office required nobles to live in the capital every other year with the alternate attendance policy. Douglas MacArthur informally held this title in recognition of his time as military governor of a certain occupied country. This office was dissolved in the Boshin War following the victory of Emperor Meiji’s forces. For 10 points, name this military office that governed Japan on behalf of the nominal emperor. "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this country that experienced extreme hyperinflation under a leader who was overthrown in 2017, Robert Mugabe. This country was formerly known as Rhodesia. ","answer":"ANSWER: Republic of Zimbabwe "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] This man lead Rhodesia’s white minority government during the Rhodesian Bush War. He consented to hand power over to Abel Muzorewa in the Lancaster House Agreement. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ian Smith "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] In Operation Murambatsvina, or “Operation Move the Rubbish,” Mugabe ordered the Zimbabwean government to destroy these locations. These places are known as favelas in Brazil ","answer":"ANSWER: slums [or shanty towns; prompt on neighborhoods or towns] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this sun deity. This son of Viracocha had his cult expanded by Pachacuti and was married to the Moon goddess Mama Killa. ","answer":"ANSWER: Inti "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Inti was the major god of this civilization, which also worshipped spirits known as Apu. The Andean Condor was considered sacred by this large South American civilization. ","answer":"ANSWER: Inca Empire [or Incan Empire] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] The Inca creator god Viracocha created humanity from these objects. In Greek mythology, Pyrrha and Deucalion threw some of these objects over their shoulders to create humanity after the Great Flood. ","answer":"ANSWER: stones [or rocks] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this dimensionless quantity, which can quantify the strength of a bond. It is equal to 2 for a double bond. ","answer":"ANSWER: bond order [prompt on “BO”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] The aforementioned formula to calculate bond order comes from this theory, which describes chemical bonding and electron positions in molecules using bonding, nonbonding, and antibonding interactions. ","answer":"ANSWER: molecular orbital theory [or MO theory; or Hund-Mulliken theory) "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Molecular orbital theory is commonly used to model these bonds. Unlike ionic bonds, these bonds involve the sharing of electron pairs between atoms. ","answer":"ANSWER: covalent bonds [accept dative bonds; accept coordinate (covalent) bonds] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this religious figure. In an another chiaroscuro painting by the same artist, a beam of light emerging from the upper-right shines on this bearded figure, who points at himself. ","answer":"ANSWER: St. Matthew "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] This Italian Baroque master and notoriously aggressive street brawler painted The Calling of St. Matthew. ","answer":"ANSWER: Michelangelo Merisi da Caravaggio "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Caravaggio modeled Christ’s hand in The Calling of St. Matthew after the pose of an arm in this painting. Gynecologist Frank Meshberger is among those who argue that the right portion of this painting depicts a human brain. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Creation of Adam [prompt on the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this author who defended Romanticism in the preface to his play Cromwell. This playwright of Hernani was inspired by Guernsey’s fisherman to write Toilers of the Sea. ","answer":"ANSWER: Victor Hugo "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] William Wordsworth gave his own defense of Romanticism in his preface to this poetry collection, which contains Wordsworth’s “Lines written above Tintern Abbey.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Lyrical Ballads "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Wordsworth and Hugo’s prefaces are collected in a Book of Prefaces by Alasdair Gray, a contemporary author from this country. This country’s greatest poet Robert Burns wrote an ode to a “lassie” from this country’s Highlands region. ","answer":"ANSWER: Scotland [prompt on United Kingdom or U.K] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this number of major political parties in America. Each individual state is granted this number of seats in the United States Senate. ","answer":"ANSWER: two [or two-party system] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] According to Robert Michels, a democracy inevitably devolves into of these systems, in which power is held by a small number of people. Michels’ theory is known as the “iron law” of these systems. ","answer":"ANSWER: oligarchy "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Michels belonged to an Italian sociological school devoted to the study of these people. A 1956 C. Wright Mills book posits that these people are the answer to the question “Who, after all, runs America?” ","answer":"ANSWER: elites [or The Power Elite; prompt on descriptive answers like rich people] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name these rules that determine which electronic transitions between orbitals are allowed in a molecule. ","answer":"ANSWER: selection rules "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] The Laporte selection rule only applies to centrosymmetric molecules, which means that they have a “center” of this process. This process involves taking a point at (x,y,z) [“x y z”] and moving it to (-x,-y,-z) [“negative x negative y negative z”]. ","answer":"ANSWER: inversion center "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Selection rules are relevant to this spectroscopic technique, which analyzes bond vibration. This technique is named after a region of the electromagnetic spectrum with wavelength longer than visible light. ","answer":"ANSWER: infrared spectroscopy [or IR; accept infrared radiation] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this field of study practiced by Colin McPhee. A pioneer of this field named Alan Lomax used the Cantometrics system and visited Angola Prison to make recordings of Huddie “Leadbelly” Ledbetter. ","answer":"ANSWER ethnomusicology [prompt on musicology; prompt on ethnography; prompt on anthropology; prompt on folklore] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Both Jaap Kunst and Colin McPhee studied the gamelan percussion ensembles of this country. Wayang shadow puppets often perform to gamelan music on this country’s islands of Java and Bali. ","answer":"ANSWER: Republic of Indonesia "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Lomax made recordings of Leadbelly at Angola Prison in this state, which is the birthplace of zydeco music. The Preservation Hall brass band hails from this state, as did the members of the Original Dixieland Jass Band. ","answer":"ANSWER: Louisiana "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this monologue performed by the sad fool Jaques. In this speech, Jacques claims that life ends “sans teeth, sans eyes, sans taste, sans everything” in “second childishness and mere oblivion.” You can provide either the common name or the first few words of it. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Seven Ages of Man speech [or the “All the world’s a stage” speech] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] The “Seven Ages of Man” monologue is delivered in this play set in the Forest of Arden. Rosalind disguises herself as a shepherd to woo Orlando in this Shakespeare play. ","answer":"ANSWER: As You Like It "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] As You Like It is an example of this Shakespearean genre. Usually contrasted with tragedies and histories, plays in this genre tend to end with weddings. ","answer":"ANSWER: comedy [or comedies] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this first president of the French Fifth Republic. This general became a national hero for his leadership of the Free French during World War II. ","answer":"ANSWER: Charles de Gaulle "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Student protests and a general workers’ strike in May of this year nearly brought down De Gaulle’s government. During the crisis of this year, de Gaulle briefly fled France to hide in Baden-Baden, Germany. ","answer":"ANSWER: 1968 [prompt on 68] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] De Gaulle’s flight to Baden-Baden soured his relationship with this prime minister, who negotiated the Grenelle Agreements to try and end the crisis. ","answer":"ANSWER: Georges Pompidou "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this piece that uses the melody from the song “La Mantovana” as its main theme. This movement of a larger work depicts a moonlight “dance of the nymphs” and shares its melody with the Israeli national anthem. ","answer":"ANSWER: Die Moldau [or Vltava; or The Moldau; prompt on Ma vlast] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Die Moldau appears alongside pieces depicting Sarka and Blanik in Ma vlast, a set of nationalistic symphonic poems by this composer. He also composed The Bartered Bride. ","answer":"ANSWER: Bedřich Smetana "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Má vlast pays tribute to the Bohemian folklore of this modern-day country, Smetana's homeland. Smetana composed patriotic marches to celebrate an uprising in this country’s city of Prague. ","answer":"ANSWER: Czech Republic [or Czechia] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name these chargeless, nearly massless leptons that rarely interact with matter. About 65 billion of them pass through each square centimeter of Earth per second. ","answer":"ANSWER: neutrinos "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Like neutrino detection, the detection of these ripples in spacetime by observatories such as LIGO are advancements in “multi-messenger” astronomy. ","answer":"ANSWER: gravitational waves [or gravity waves or gravitational radiation; prompt on waves] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Neutrinos emitted from a supernova were first directly recorded with the occurrence of SN 1987A in this Local Group system. After the Andromeda Galaxy, it is one of the closest galaxies to the Milky Way. ","answer":"ANSWER: Large Magellanic Cloud [prompt on Magellanic Cloud] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this novel about Newland Archer’s affair with Countess Ellen Olenska. In this novel, Newland’s plan to run away with the Countess is foiled when his wife May Welland becomes pregnant. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Age of Innocence "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] This author of The Age of Innocence wrote about the title Starkfield resident’s affection for Mattie Silver in Ethan Frome. ","answer":"ANSWER: Edith Wharton "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] In Ethan Frome, Ethan and Mattie attempt to commit suicide in this manner. Ethan repeats “I know we can fetch it” while carrying out this action before seeing his wife Zenobia’s face. ","answer":"ANSWER: sledding into a tree [accept any answer mentioning sledding] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this indigenous people that resides in the northern regions of Norway, Sweden and Finland. ","answer":"ANSWER: Sami [accept Lapps or Laplanders, but inform the player that these terms are considered derogatory] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Traditionally, the Sami people reside in saavu huts which are made from the hides of this animal. The poem “A Visit from St. Nicholas” spread the legend that these animals pull Santa Claus’ sleigh. ","answer":"ANSWER: reindeer [or caribou] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] The majority of Russia’s Sami population live on this peninsula, which separates the White Sea from the Barents Sea. Its largest city is Murmansk. ","answer":"ANSWER: Kola Peninsula "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this body of water named for a marooned explorer who captained the Half Moon. The drainage basin of this body of water was awarded to its namesake company as Rupert’s Land. ","answer":"ANSWER: Hudson Bay [or Hudson’s Bay Company] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] The Hudson’s Bay Company primarily traded for this commodity, which it harvested from beavers. ","answer":"ANSWER: fur [or pelts; or equivalents] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] These mixed-race Canadian people descend from the union of fur traders and First Nations women. After Canada purchased Rupert’s Land, Louis Riel led a revolt of these people. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Métis [prompt on descriptive answers, such as mixed-race Canadians or half-Indian Canadians] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this contemporary American philosopher who used a thought experiment involving an “unconscious violinist” to critique the “right to life” argument in her paper “A Defense of Abortion.”. ","answer":"ANSWER: Judith (Jarvis) Thomson "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Thomson added a “fat man” to this popular thought experiment, in which a person can save five people from an out-of-control vehicle if they redirect the vehicle to hit someone else. ","answer":"ANSWER: the trolley problem [accept any equivalents that include trolley] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Judith Thomson is a prominent thinker within the “virtue” field of this branch of philosophy, which attempts to determine right from wrong. ","answer":"ANSWER: ethics [or moral philosophy; accept virtue ethics] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this Christian holy day that derives its most common name from its commemoration of the foot washing of Jesus and his apostles. ","answer":"ANSWER: Maundy Thursday [or Holy Thursday; or Covenant Thursday; or Great and Holy Thursday; or Sheer Thursday; or Thursday of Mysteries] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Maundy Thursday occurs on the Thursday before this major Christian holiday whose date was historically set by the Computus. This holiday celebrates Jesus’ resurrection from the dead. ","answer":"ANSWER: Easter [or Pascha; or Resurrection Sunday] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] A large, white one of these objects is typically blessed and used every year at Easter. A cross, the letters alpha and omega, and the current year are typically displayed on that object of this kind. ","answer":"ANSWER: a candle "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this night. It is the night after Dunyazade attends her sister’s wedding to King Shahryar and the book those characters appear in ends. ","answer":"ANSWER: the 1002nd night [prompt on descriptive answers like “the last night of the Arabian Nights” that do not specifically mention the number 1002; do not accept or prompt on the 1001st night] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] In the 1001 Nights, this woman puts off her marriage to King Shahryar by telling him a story each night. ","answer":"ANSWER: Scheherazade [10] 1,001 children are born at midnight on Indian Indepence Day in this author’s novel Midnight’s Children. This author was forced to go into hiding after he received a fatwa for his novel The Satanic Verses. "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this molecule which tags proteins in the Golgi apparatus that are destined for lysosomes. ","answer":"ANSWER: mannose-6-phosphate [or M6P; or man-6-P] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] This other lysosomal storage disease is caused by a mutation in HEXA [“HECK-sah”] genes and results in the buildup of GM2 gangliosides in neurons. It is prevalent among Cajuns and Ashkenazi Jews. ","answer":"ANSWER: Tay-Sachs disease "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Enzymes responsible for lysosomal function are synthesized by this organelle’s “rough” variety, which is studded by numerous ribosomes. ","answer":"ANSWER: rough endoplasmic reticulum [or the ER] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"5. An iconic photograph depicts a line of evacuees attempting to board a small helicopter on the roof of this city’s American embassy. ","answer":"ANSWER: Saigon [or Ho Chi Minh City] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] While US troops began withdrawing from South Vietnam during Nixon’s presidency, this president was in office during the fall of Saigon. He became president after Nixon resigned during the Watergate scandal. ","answer":"ANSWER: Gerald Ford [or Leslie Lynch King] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] This politician allowed the CIA to operate out of Saigon’s US embassy during his time as President Kennedy’s Ambassador to South Vietnam. He was Richard Nixon’s running mate in the 1960 presidential election. ","answer":"ANSWER: Henry Cabot Lodge Jr. [or Henry Cabot Lodge II; prompt on Henry Cabot Lodge; do not accept or prompt on Henry Cabot Lodge Sr.] Tiebreaker. To prove that these numbers exist, Joseph Liouville constructed a decimal consisting of ones in digit places that correspond to factorials, and zeros otherwise. For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name these numbers that are not the solution to any polynomial with rational coefficients. In addition to being irrational, pi and e are examples of these numbers. ","answer":"ANSWER: transcendental numbers "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] The “common” form of this operation yields a transcendental number if it is not applied to a power of 10. [Read slowly] Given a base b and a number x, this operation gives a such that b to the a equals x. ","answer":"ANSWER: common logarithm [or base-10 logarithm] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] The seventh member of this set of mathematical problems asks whether a to the b will be transcendental if a is not 0 or 1 and b is irrational. ","answer":"ANSWER: Hilbert’s problems EXTRA One of this man’s films, loosely adapted from Dostoevsky’s The Possessed, centers on a group of Maoist university students who attempt to assassinate the Soviet Minister of Culture. For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Name this founder of the Dziga Vertov Group. This frequent collaborator of Anna Karina featured an intertitle about “The Children of Marx and Coca-Cola” in a film whose title translates to Masculine Feminine. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jean-Luc Godard "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Godard was a pioneer in a radical French film movement of the 60s that rejected the “Tradition of Quality” and was described by this two-word name. It was championed by André Bazin’s Cahiers du Cinéma magazine. ","answer":"ANSWER: French New Wave [or La Nouvelle Vague] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"F","question":"[10] Michel, the protagonist of Godard’s Breathless, loves to mimic the style of this American actor. He starred in films like The Big Sleep, The Maltese Falcon, and Casablanca. ","answer":"ANSWER: Humphrey Bogart"}]
